this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
c-radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society by IEEE software
Magazine online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
I'm your host Gavin Henry and today my
guest is Michael Fazio
Michael is a software developer and Tech
speaker who fell in love with Android
starting with the original Samsung
Galaxy S way back in 2010 he's been the
Android lead for multiple billion dollar
companies and is the author of kotlin
and Android development featuring
Jetpack from the pragmatic programmers
Michael welcome to software engineering
radio is there anything I missed in the
bio that you'd like to add yeah it
sounds great I'm also the engineering
manager for the Android team with Albert
Financial startup in the the US
and so we're trying to help normal
people Americans it's complicated enough
trying to just view the US
and trying to make sure
people have the advice and tools they
need to get their financial space in
place so I get to use Android and help
normal Americans get in a better spot
cool thank you so the goals for the show
today is to understand where Android is
right now to discuss a brief possibly
paint history of Android mobile
development
and what it's like now you know problem
modern Android development also I'd like
to understand and the lessons to
understand when to reach for like native
Android development versus some of the
other Frameworks that try to create apps
for all different platforms so let's get
started Android operating system what is
it today can you describe that for us so
it's at the point today where it's the
most used mobile platform around the
world I was trying to get updated
numbers it's at least three billion
devices at this point that was from last
year funny enough it actually started as
a digital camera operating system and
the team at Android Inc went
this might get better reach being a a
phone OS and that turned out to be the
case
and so yeah it's now on phones
everywhere tablets you can run Android
apps on Chromebooks on Windows there's
Android TV there's Android auto and
where OS which are effectively different
display types for
the you know your phone so you have your
phone it runs everything but then you
display it in a different way in your
car dealing with things on your wrist
all of that and that's native isn't it
that's not yes
yeah so there's just a few shows that I
want to mention to the listeners before
we get on to the next section
um so we did a show episode 326 on
kotlin I did a show episode four three
seven with Tim Smith who's the head of
flutter Matt Lacy episode 428 on mobile
app usability which is a really good one
if you haven't heard that one Michael
show 427 on mobile application security
because there's a lot of surface area to
think about when you're doing these and
then lastly episode 300 Jonathan Stark
on mobile app development again so
obviously Android is everywhere you know
three billion devices at least and loads
of different shapes and forms can you
give us some examples briefly of
problems you've had experience in
developing it since you got involved
sort of 2010. the number one thing I
always call out is the fact that there
are so many devices by so many different
makers that you have a lot of choice
with what you want to have in a an
Android device you know if you want
bigger screens smaller screen more
powerful cameras whatever it might be
the issue from the dev side is that that
level of fragmentation means you have to
account for a whole bunch of different
devices and some devices will display
things differently some will run things
differently some like Samsung devices
are much more aggressive in how often
they close out your app and so then you
have to recreate it and make sure that
when it's recreated it comes back
exactly as you expect and so trying to
deal with all these different form
factors device makers everything like
that can pose a lot of problems and it's
gotten better
some of the jetpack libraries that we'll
touch on a little bit later have helped
that but it's still definitely a
challenge to say all right I've got my
pixel phone somebody else has a Galaxy
phone
does this look the same or not how do I
get them to match up what can I do here
past that there's always challenges with
the life cycle of all right the app is
spinning up an activity which we'll talk
about in a bit is spinning up
what are the steps it goes through what
part do I need to jump into how do I
handle when a new activity is coming up
and another one's going away jumping
between them all of that can be a
challenge and then just navigation
between different views and trying to
figure out all right here's where I want
to be here's where I need to go
what's a kind of a smooth way to do that
and so there's all these different
pieces in there also in the fact that
when you're dealing with these
applications they're on somebody else's
Hardware it's a lot out of your control
and you just have to kind of hope it's
working well for them with again the
different devices different styles
different form factors different network
situations all these other variables
that you don't necessarily have with
like a traditional website on a PC is
this because you know you've got all
these different devices in different
countries there's a device issue or is
it the thought that you're not dealing
with the same range of Android versions
or do you have to make a decision so you
know what we can only support a certain
version of Android that's up to five
years old for example can you kind of
make a decision there and say we presume
that everyone has a back button presume
everyone has a screen of at least this
size I mean how do you work around them
and how does it impact the user
at some point you just have to you have
to have that cut off and say okay we'll
support old versions of the OS in
comparison to iOS it's usually people
upgrade very fast for their OS version
the you know you have a small set of
devices and everything's ready to go on
Android like in our example the current
version API version I want to say is 33
and we support back to 21 for this is
for the Albert app and we do that to
make sure that people that bought
devices six seven years ago that may
have been slightly out of date then can
still use their app but there's a lot of
challenges that does pose and so in
combination with what I mentioned before
about the different devices yeah the
different Android versions can be a
challenge as well some things are back
ported some things aren't so it's just
there's a much wider range of
environments that you're dealing with
when you're going ahead and you're
you're working with Android devices and
this is not even talking about getting
into tablets and all the other pieces I
mentioned earlier this is just talking
about phones there's that huge range so
this might impact a user by
the fact that you won't be able to do a
certain feature on a certain Android
version and just explain what you mean
by apis versus Android 8 and 9 and 10
how does that work so it's the same
thing it's just a different way to refer
to it so when we talk about an Android 8
9 I think
13 is the current one it's code name
tiramisu because they always had their
fun sweet dessert names for them
and so the new ones 13 codename tiramisu
but it's API level 33. there's kind of
these different names for the same thing
so the users are looking at Android 13
the developers are going all right
here's the API level
33 because minor updates to Android
versions use that API level and the API
level is what is really controlling
what's available just built into the OS
so you say all right I'm targeting this
and then I have some other version
that's my minimum
the device needs to be running this but
I'm really hoping they're running this
better one because then I can get
everything included over here and then
have fallbacks for any situation where
oh this isn't supported with a lower
version of the OS
yeah that makes sense so you can either
way up
how much effort we need to put in to
make it look or detect on these older
things or just say we can't do it and it
won't be available through the Play
Store because of that version limitation
exactly it's like we just have to say
all right we here's the experience we
want here's the threshold it needs to be
we can't support every device we can't
test every device
we've got tools to simulate that but
it's not going to be perfect and that's
just something that we have to accept
and make sure that we are hitting the
devices that our users
are using the most
and just before I move us on to the next
bit we should also touch upon the fact
that because Android is open source you
can't really guarantee that you're on
API 33 because a vendor might do
something to it to make it work on there
no proprietary Hardware
yeah they all have their own way to
implement different things in their own
tweaks and Spins and here's our version
of the UI it's similar but it's not
quite the same and it can work a little
weird so it's like there's the bass line
and then there's the parts added on by
the different vendors exactly as you
said I suppose it's the freedom thing
you know Samsung do one thing HTC used
to do one thing and you've got so many
all the different bandars whereas if you
go Apple it's one way or no way you know
yep
exactly it's like the beauty of Android
is you have the freedom to get the
device and the layout and everything you
want you can swap out the the Home
Launcher you can do all these things
but it's also the danger of it of oh
things don't work consistently on every
device it's like yeah because you have
that freedom it's not quite as safe it's
not quite as uniform as you'd expect
from comparison to iOS yeah they might
have taken a different kernel as well
you just never know I think we touched
upon all the different range of Hardware
that Android works on so my next
question would be
as a developer when do you choose to go
native as in proper Android like we're
talking about or you go for a framework
like react native or flutter or one of
the other ones out there that's still
surviving because you want to make a
mobile app that works on iOS desktop
weapon Android type things
could you share any sort of best
practices or anything you've experienced
of what makes that decision clear-cut
what's always funny because I've had
people ask me that and I'll be sitting
here presenting about Native Android
development they're like oh so don't do
cross-platform like no no the
cross-platform tools now are really good
and they make us make sense in a lot of
cases
and the quick one I always give is is
your team big enough to support two
completely separate apps separate
platforms separate languages separate
Integrations
or are you in a spot where I need to
have one code base because my team can't
handle it we don't have the resources we
don't have the knowledge I've also seen
it before where let's say I had a client
like this years ago of all right
everybody knows.net everybody can do C
sharp
we need a mobile app let's use xamarin
because it's c-sharp our team already
has the language part done again we're
not big enough to support twofold teams
for
two full apps instead we can have a Dev
team and the mobile app is just another
part of that
there's extra challenges with the mobile
app but you at least have the ability to
come in and look and go I can read the
code that makes sense
it's one of those where if you just want
to get something small up and running
your cross-platform tools are going to
be great if your main concern is I want
my app to be smooth it's I don't care if
it's basic I don't care what it does I
just want this thing to look smooth as
possible flutter may be your best bet
because that's such a focus of that
Library
but if you're in a situation where you
can support the multiple teams you want
the best possible experience out of your
app you want to be able to use multiple
third-party libraries without issue
you're going to want to go native then
that is the ideal State like that's the
intended state for an app is the native
approach
when you say with the native app
is there more stability in the libraries
that you choose versus because I've done
a flatter app and I'm just working on my
next one and there's so much movement on
releases I just I was hoping you'd say
in the Android worlds you get a bit more
stability depending on what you're using
you know there's
potentially the last choice of libraries
because there's you know you're going
native so you don't
have all these different hooks what
would you say to that yeah absolutely
it's so much easier to go and bring in
something third party when you're
dealing with a native app I know again
going from my xamarin experience
bringing this app here's all this extra
work we have to do to get it to work
with xamarin unless you get lucky and
somebody else has done that for you and
shared it otherwise you're doing that by
hand you go in on Android and you say
all right here's my library I'm going to
use here's the version put it in my
Gradle file sync hey I've got a library
you're done that's all you need to do
with it and it's kind of nice thinking
about you're talking about having the
new versions and having to deal with
that whereas you get something like the
jetpack libraries
and not only are they out there and
they're easy to put into an app but
they're all separately versioned so you
don't have to upgrade Everything at Once
even if you want part of your one of
your jetpack libraries to be newer you
can upgrade the single one and it
doesn't have to be the full Suite so I'm
jumping ahead but it's another spot
where it gets to be easier to deal with
as opposed to which you have other is no
that's perfect next session we're gonna
dig into the actual programming language
call in a my Android has adopted it why
it's so popular but just to close off
this section about the Android operating
system in general could be suspend some
time on you taking this through a new
experience obviously
creating a traditional Android mobile
app before kotlin and Jetpack came
around
yeah and some of this stuff is
absolutely still true you come into an
Android app you have an activity that is
the main driver for an app it's your
main view it's what starts up it's it's
kind of a heavyweight component but it
has all these things it can do in there
and so even now you set up an Android
app you need to have at least one
activity that is your your main
piece and then you can build up from
there
but what would happen is before you'd be
going ahead and you create an activity
and it would have your view components
it would probably be accessing data
somewhere in there you know maybe you
can have a separation of concerns a
little bit where you'd create some other
classes to do that and it can just
somewhat tie into the activity you want
a new view okay now we're going to go
ahead and we're going to jump this new
activity and you're running these
intents back and forth which again still
done when you're going between
activities
but before it was that was your view
component that's the only option you had
and so you're you're losing all your
contacts all your data from the activity
and you have to spin it up in the new
one and then you're sending parameters
through when you're starting up this new
activity that's there you're doing all
of this tied to an XML file which is
where your your layout lives and most
apps are still XML based but it would go
ahead and it would say okay here's my
activity from a code perspective here's
my Java file with an activity here's my
XML layout file for that activity and
I'm specifying the layouts you know I
usually have like some kind of frame
layout that's my container I've got a
linear layout that's some number of
components in a row
got a maybe I'll have a list view where
I can go ahead and I can bring multiple
things in so it's scrollable if you had
too many it might get really slow really
fast
you're also dealing with other
resources within XML files it might be
string values because you can do
translations it might be Dimension files
which are different sizes or values you
use in layouts that are set
so you're doing all this you're doing it
all in Eclipse back in the day so it was
eclipsed with an Android plug-in didn't
have its own IDE
a you're doing this in Java you're
trying to make async calls somewhere
else but you have to use async tasks
which is an entire class you're
overwriting methods and specifying okay
before and after and you're creating a
brand new class every time you're going
out to some third-party location you're
directly accessing the SQL Lite database
on the device you're getting a cursor
back you're manually going through the
cursor saying all right while the cursor
has data take it out convert everything
to what you want make it an actual
object you can use send it out
all this by the way being done on an
emulator that barely worked that was one
of those I'm like I'm very realistic
about this the emulator was awful for
years and so usually okay if I can get a
device and you develop on that
my life's a lot easier not everybody
would have that luxury so it was like
I've worked on worse things but it
wasn't great and when people would
complain about oh I have to do this and
this and this I'd go yeah that's fair
it's not the best developer experience
and so there's been a lot of changes
that have been made to help the tooling
make movement around an app simpler to
make displaying data simpler to make
saving data simpler accessing data
simpler all these ways that here's what
we had we had to start there but it's
definitely better than this Android
development was back in 2014 for example
even when you got all that right did you
still have
a potentially unstable app or is that
improved as well there's always that
chance with it again talking about the
fragmentation
we would go ahead and there was fewer
devices but there are still multiple
devices and in a way it was a little bit
more challenging because nowadays A lot
of people are going to have Samsung
devices a good number are going to have
the Google pixel devices and then
there's some people that have smaller
offshoot devices whereas before it was a
little bit more of an even playing
Ground where you had
LG and Motorola and I think Nokia had a
little bit in there
and
Samsung was still in there you know
maybe Google was coming in a little bit
later on the fragmentation is still
there but it's the major devices are a
smaller set than it was
and then you're hoping everything worked
and that your emulator showed a
reasonable enough
version of the app so that you can test
and say okay here's what I'm expecting
people to see
but wasn't even a guarantee
and I noticed there's Android studio now
which isn't the eclipse and yes I plug
in which is actually really nice I
really like using that but you just
remind me touching on the emulators
there there aren't that many emulators
to choose from in Android Studio that's
all no older things how does that impact
using all the modern jetpack things but
you've got
potentially older devices you're
simulating on well and they're more
generic devices they're not all right
here let me do an emulator that's a
Samsung Galaxy S10 Plus
let me go ahead and have a I mean
they've got the pixel 6 Pro but it's not
a perfect
example of how things will work so
you're you're doing that but it's not
great this is why there are tools like
Firebase has their device set where you
can say I'm going to test this section
of my app and I'm going to do it against
these 10 devices
and it's going to go run them against
like the actual devices that are out
there as opposed to trying to use an
emulator and going
I think this is how this is supposed to
work except I have the real device and
it's not you're playing a bit of a
guessing game and so even now it's like
it's still a challenge with it it's it
was worse back then because they didn't
perform and they weren't laid out nicely
but that is still definitely a a
sticking point when you're trying to
test things out properly and make sure
it works well and Firebase is the Google
Soft service isn't it yes and they've
got all things like real-time database
crashlytics for tracking again the
device testing and 30 other tools I'm
not even touching on here
excellent thank you okay let's draw a
line into the Android operating system
and drill into
the kotlin programming language what is
kotlin so catelyn's a just it's a
multi-purpose strongly typed language
you can think of it as the next
evolution of a Java I always like
describing it as we took Java we learned
about it for years we ran it through the
book Effective Java by Josh block and we
got kotlin out of it it can be used for
all kinds of different places I'm
spoiling stuff ahead of time and
it's a really really nice language with
functional Parts it's object oriented
and has a bunch of Time Savers as
compared to what we were using in Java
all out the book to the show notes if
it's still something you recommend yeah
absolutely so why was kotlin created and
by who it always makes me chuckle
because it was created by jet brains
which is the company that makes IntelliJ
or webstorm pie charm Android Studio
which is a skin of IntelliJ focused on
Android development
and they're like all right we want a jvm
language
and we want something with more modern
features than we get from java
scala's got them except Scala
compilation times are really slow so
what does a developer to do
they create their own language because
that's what we do we create our own
things and so they built out their own
jvm languages back in 2010 they kicked
it off they finally told about it in
2011. version one didn't even come out
until 2016. so it's
not a brand new language but it's fairly
new if you're looking at something like
a Java that's been around for 30 years
and even C sharp which is still newer
than Java but still been around for a
while yes younger than go as well is
quite new and so it's the this new
language they put out I would say it's
like it's probably a little bit too of
hey here's this new awesome jvm language
it works great in IntelliJ why don't you
buy IntelliJ and use it with it which
again I've got my own library or my own
license for IntelliJ and everything it
does work great
and what are the main benefits for us is
still doing Android and Java which I
presume you can do yep you can choose if
you want to use Java you want to use
kotlin you want to use both for a little
bit of history in 2017 Google went at
Google I O is like hey kotlin this jvm
language that's out here just went 1.0
last year you can use this just like you
use Java in Android apps it is a first
class language for Android development
then 2019 they go you know what
why don't you go with kotlin first we're
recommending kotlin as the main language
because it offers everything Java does
but it has more features on top of it
and also allows the Android team to put
things in that are kotlin specific which
will end up working better
and I think there's a little bit of
incentive for Google to say let's get
away from java and Oracle and everything
going over here let's go with this other
language with a partner
that works with us with jetbrains see
more of a political type thing
potentially I think that was part of it
too but it is again it is to me a nicer
language to be using and there's a whole
bunch of reasons for it
so the number one I always love calling
out is
they shifted to a system where no safety
is built in
meaning a nullable object something that
can be null so in in Java you have a
string and that string can be any kind
of text or it can be null so it's kind
of two different objects because it's an
actual value and then it's nothing
in kotlin you have a string which is
some text value
or you can have a nullable string which
means I know this could be null at some
point and kotlin at compile time makes
you go ahead and handle those null
scenarios
and so it's instead of it being okay I'm
running along and oh shoot I don't have
data here and I'm expecting to have data
and your app blows up kotlin's making
you handle all this all of those
scenarios I remember working on a
c-sharp app and this was a flag you
could turn on I'm like this is great
you're not sitting there getting bit by
no pointer exceptions in different
places when really we probably should
have been handling this in the first
place that null safety is so nice for
the stability of an app like from a
security perspective it's better like
it's a huge part of it but in addition
there's a lot less boilerplate when
you're dealing with kotlin this is
something that when people come from
other languages and they're looking at
Java they're like
there's a lot of stuff you have to write
to really get to what you want between
the the Getters and Setters and going
ahead and having multiple Constructors
and all these pieces when it's it's not
really necessary it's not what you're
going for
you instead with kotlin can really get
to things quickly you get data classes
which are your kind of your pojos so
your plain old Java objects that you'd
have normally it'd be all right I'm
going to have user object with 20 fields
on it each one of those fields may have
a getter insetter or at least a getter
and then I've got five different
Constructors based on where I want that
to be instead you go ahead in kotlin you
create a data class you have all those
fields in the one Constructor if some of
them are optional you can go ahead and
Define a default value and maybe it's
making them null and making them
nullable fields or you can go ahead and
just assign if you've got a string
you're like I don't want this to be no
I defaulted to an empty string and I
really only have to fill in
five of the fields let's say it's all
this flexibility to give you one
Constructor the Getters and Setters are
generated for you you can make multiple
Constructors if you want you have that
flexibility but you don't need to do it
out of the box touching back on the null
safety part yes that makes kotlin
potentially more secure doesn't it yep
because if you're running through
scenarios where you're going through
security checks and all of a sudden you
get a null pointer exception in the
middle that you're not expecting
and oh I'm trying to check this up I
blew up well I guess my checks are fine
because I didn't finish them
all of a sudden now people are let
through
it's
you know it gets rid of these unknown
scenarios these scenarios you're not
expecting that would be there otherwise
it sounds like you should just start off
with kotlin anyway because you won't
have to do all the painful things you
used to do in Java I still do and can
you use Java Frameworks with kotlin the
big one I remember is spring that does
pretty much everything
yep there's probably some scenario where
you can't use kotlin with a Java app but
basically every place you use Java you
can use kotlin now so talking about
spring
not only is it now as of spring five you
add kotlin as a dependency and you can
do whatever you need to but if you go to
start.spring.io you go to the spring
initializer one of the options there is
like do you want your app in Java or do
you want it in kotlin I think they might
actually offer groovy as well if I
remember correctly but it's seen again
as a first class language for spring
development now I will say if you are in
a scenario where you want to use kotlin
completely and you want some of the the
API features you get from Spring boot
you can go ahead and use something like
kator which is a jetbrains library that
they've created framework I should say
it's fully kotlin you can do the server
side you can actually have a client as
well that you pull out of it that will
use the same types that are in there
it's got websocket support it's got
co-routine support which we haven't even
touched on yet for asynchronous calls
like all these really nice kotlin
features are just built into ktor
whereas spring was originally built more
for Java it may be missing some of those
but even newer versions of spring offer
some nice flexibility with what you can
do with kotlin there that you couldn't
do before it would be good if we can
scoop this up in the show notes for some
recommended libraries you know a lot of
them people trying to find these all out
yeah absolutely it's a bit of a silly
question but this does kotlin just for
Android operating system or it's not and
that's not a silly question because
that's where it's been pushed a lot I
remember one of the first times I did a
kotlin talk I was at that conference in
Wisconsin Dells here in Wisconsin large
Regional Tech conference and I'm like
all right are we talking about kotlin
it's going to be a bunch of Android
people in here and I'll just make sure
I'm tailoring that to them and so I get
in there and I'm like hey before we
start what do people work on who are my
Android people and I've got I don't know
how many people in the room
a quarter of the people raise their hand
for Android who's doing jvm server-side
development and two-thirds raise their
hand I'm like oh okay I need to tweak
this slightly as I go here like I'm
gonna we're gonna change this on the Fly
slightly because
all these people on the Java side were
like well I can use this right like this
seems like this works is this gonna be
better and so yeah you can use it
um again anywhere you're using Java you
can use kotlin it's obviously this first
class language now an Android but if
you're doing spring apps like we talked
about you can do it there there's
actually the ability now on the client
side to use this and this is saying
kotlin can be compiled down into
JavaScript es5 JavaScript you can go
ahead and you can pile it down there's a
create react app version
that is using kotlin that's out there
that I think jetbrains actually created
as well you can go ahead and use kotlin
native to build things for Mac OS and it
works actually on iOS if you're taking
advantage of something like kotlin
multi-platform which is a whole separate
discussion in theory I haven't done this
but in theory with Forge which is a mod
library for Minecraft you can build
Minecraft mods using kotlin it should
work everywhere that Java is and so we
look a lot at the Android side of things
but it is certainly not exclusive to
just being on Android
I heard you mentioned Co routines and
that's something that always pops into
my head when
I read or see kotlin is that something
that you could do in Java or what are
they and why is it a good thing
so core routines the very simple version
is they're what you use for asynchronous
development they're kind of like
lightweight threads
but in the background they're really
able to run on any type of thread and so
from a practical perspective they're
what you use now because I mentioned
before about async tasks in Android
applications and you're overwriting a
whole class and doing all this to really
get like three pieces of code to work
here's what I want to do before during
and after not
with co-routines you can say all right
I'm gonna go and run a co-routine over
in my Android app here's my co-routine
scope I'm going to run X Y and Z
functions they are called suspending
functions this is similar to what people
think of as like async await in a
c-sharp or JavaScript
you have an async function which is
called a suspend function or a
suspending function in kotlin
you can run whatever you want in that
co-routine block you have multiple
suspending functions or non-suspending
even they can run sequentially in the
block
and then you can react to it something
at the end and that is going to be run
on a different thread asynchronously on
its own
which leads to a lot of models with
Android where I make a call over here I
run something asynchronously and then I
have an event listener to let my view
know when the processing is done and
with using some of the libraries that
are out there that gets much much easier
so it's this really really nice way to
handle
asynchronous
development while
not having to worry about so many of the
pieces where they move around you're
like you're basically just calling stuff
sequentially
but in the background it's running off
your UI thread out of the way and it
does exactly what you need with it yeah
it sounds a bit similar to
isolates and dark
chat about on a different show
and in Airline and elixir you've got the
threads that run not as native threads
but
kind of like core routines I think yep
and I don't think I've asked but we've
stated that kotlin was developed by jet
brains
it's open source doesn't it it's a free
programming language it's not a
proprietary one correct yeah I thought
I'd just highlight that okay so just to
finish off this section on kotlin unless
there's anything exciting that you've
not thought to say
you know when someone says why should I
use kotlin
you know there's something on the list
that hasn't come out I mean I could go
on for a while about all the reasons
that I enjoy working with it from my
perspective
the lack of boilerplate from just simple
things like
not having the new keyword when you
create a new instance of something to
the ability to create a top level
function so it just here's a file with
functions that I need instead of having
to create a class every time or the fact
that you have extension functions and
extension values that are available some
of the quick little extras they have of
all right I'm creating a list I can just
do list of here's my values and it
creates a list for me instead of having
to go okay new list this all right add
these things to the list
little Parts like that or the built-in
functions like let where you take some
object and then inside a block it
creates a new instance of that same
object so if it's a mutable object that
can be changed you could do let on it it
creates a new copy of it and then you
can use it in there and now that object
is immutable or you do a null check on
that object and then you get a non-null
version of the same one inside your
block so it can be used for just making
things cleaner and to read or to do a
null check there's a ton of standard
functions that are built in you know
your map filter reduce but ones like
chunked where here's a list I'm going to
split this up into little pieces and
it's already built in zip with next
where here's a big list and I'm going to
put them in together in pairs when I was
doing Advent of code with kotlin this
last year was like all right I can use
all these crazy functions I wouldn't
necessarily normally use to try to get
my data in the right spot and it works
out great
so all the things we mentioned we've got
all of this there's all these other
pieces it just to me the summary with
kotlin is there's a lot less extra code
I have to put into my applications it
gets very very readable very easily I
mean it can get very not readable if
you're not careful I mean that's pretty
much any language but it ends up being
very readable very logical
and you just there's less in your way
and more focused on what you actually
want to get done with the code
I presume this makes working with
Android a lot more enjoyable than going
with Java
I certainly think so I mean I I think
it's a lot easier to kind of get through
especially given that there have been
some libraries where they've added
extension functions to built-in pieces
of
that are in the Android framework so for
example the old Java way of doing a
click listener would be item dot set on
clicklistener new click listener
override function on click here's my
logic and with kotlin it's set on click
listener add a block so just parentheses
or brackets around it
your code that wanted to be run that's
it
like you're getting rid of all these
other parts and so there's there's all
these nice benefits to it it just it's
easier to read it's easier to get
somebody in there you're writing less
code and it just yeah it makes
everything nicer and I try not to bash
on Java like that's where I learned how
to develop but there's a lot of benefits
to going the kotlin route
thanks Michael I'll move us on to
talking about Android jetpack now just
to close off this kotlin section
why can you still develop in Java for
Android then do you think
I think it just it's for backwards
compatibility mostly because you've got
apps out there that are written in Java
they're not ready to go ahead and
convert over a million lines of java
code to kotlin what they can do is say
all right new development's going to be
in kotlin parts of it's going to be in
Java and we can kind of have both of
them here
and I think there's a little bit you
talk about
you know we were saying before about the
multi-platform tools that are out there
saying all right maybe I don't want to
try to learn Swift and kotlin but we
know C sharp let's use xamarin you know
we know web development let's use react
native in kind of the same way people
know Java maybe we just want to stick
with Java I remember there's a survey a
couple years ago and they said hey
teams that went and had a Java Android
app switched to kotlin and then switch
back to Java what happened
and like the only reason that people
gave was
well we didn't want to learn kotlin
okay maybe you don't have time maybe
it's not the incentive
whatever it may be
it still allows them to go ahead and get
these apps out there I mean there's so
many apps out there that are Java only
you can't drop support
what they are doing though
is some of the new features in
particular jetpack compose
is kotlin only you can't use it with
Java anymore much to the Chagrin of some
of the the Java developers
so they're not maybe getting the the
latest and greatest but there's still so
much of a Java base out there for
Android that you can't dismiss that you
can't get rid of it because it doesn't
make sense
yeah I understand that I mean people
don't like change unless they're forced
too so it makes sense okay thank you for
that maybe kotlin should be a complete
show by itself there's obviously a lot
to talk about
let's move on to Android jetpack what is
Jetpack and why was it created
so jetpack is a large suite of
mainly libraries but there's also kind
of guidance I don't like using the term
best practices but basically the idea of
here's ways we recommend dealing with
your Android application
and it's all these pieces that are
created to make Android development
better easier help with fragmentation
help with older versions of Android help
get rid of some of those pain points
that we talked about earlier in the show
and so and it's Google's official
recommendation of ways to handle things
this also includes by the way like a
full guide to app architecture which In
fairness you look at and you're like
well yeah this is how you develop an
application you have your distinct
layers they don't know about each other
but it's really good to call out within
an Android context and within the scope
of Jetpack to say hey here's the
libraries here's how you can use those
to get this app architecture that we are
recommending
is it easy to describe the architecture
on a podcast episode or quick version is
it's like you have your distinct UI
layer which will have your main UI
components and then usually a view model
to handle what's going into your UI so
you have that separation of your
activity or fragment that is displaying
what you want the view model that tells
the view what to display an optional
domain layer that's you know your
complex business logic any business
logic we use and then there's the data
layer that is all right here's some of
the other business logic a little
simpler trying to get app access this
will usually have a repository or
multiple repositories in there and then
some kind of data source whether it's a
local database running something like
room which is one of the jetpack
libraries or calls out to your apis
I mean I feel like it's a fairly
standard way to look at architecture of
here's my layers UI is only focused on
UI your middle layer to really kind of
navigate things around your data layer
to figure out where things are coming
from and going
and making sure each of the pieces are
standalone
not needing to know about the other ones
at all
that's a bit more than your traditional
MVC and then you've got your model view
V model sort of JavaScript
framework style like view is there an
acronym for this at all I just yeah it's
an mvvm setup just like you described
yeah yeah cool I got that right that's
good okay so just to summarize to make
sure I understood that jetpack is a set
of libraries
to help you get around all the
traditional problems faced with Android
mobile development is recommended by
Google yep it's all these tools to make
development smoother and make things
make a little bit more sense I mean
we're talking about there's over 100
libraries that are part of the general
jetpack
umbrella it's also referred to sometimes
as Android X because that's the package
name for it is all right Android x dot
whatever you're dealing with I've seen
them
sound familiar yep and so you'll see
Android X Out There the chat yeah and so
there's a bunch of pieces within jetpack
Android X that are either the libraries
for this or they might be kotlin
extensions to make existing parts easier
I mentioned about the click listener
that's part of Android X as well there's
a whole bunch yeah it's all these
different pieces you can put into your
app to just make things smoother and
easier to deal with and does Android
Studio what's up the default to go for
that makes this all easy the jet pack
the ID yeah I mean anytime you're doing
native Android now you're going to want
to be in Android Studio because they've
got the tools in place that you want
they've they continue to upgrade it's
they just had it recently where you can
go and you can bring up access to your
your database and do Network tracing or
look through the the files on your
device or even just one recently it was
I have a physical device I'm testing on
I can do screen mirroring within Android
Studio
so I have a physical device I can use
and get all the benefits from that but I
can still see it on my screen and use my
keyboard and all of that and it's all
just built in Android Studio it's very
very handy yeah I really like Android
Studio as well it actually made me go
out and get a jetpack subscription for
some of the other programming languages
as well yep because I didn't want to
shift back to nothing wrong with him you
know I've used that for decades but yeah
it was something nice about all the
shortcuts and everything okay so I got
the summary of Jetpack correct so
libraries recommended by Google to make
Android development easier which is
kotlin so what is the infamous jetpack
compose and why is it so cool well the
funny thing about jetpack compose is
it's part of this jetpack Library set
and it's a way to go ahead and
handle your UI within code
and so I remember there's a little bit
of confusion about okay jetpack well
that means compose right it's like no no
jetpack is all these other pieces that
are out there
whereas compose is just not just but is
the UI
in your code as opposed to using XML
that's what I thought as well yeah a
couple things with just normal jetpack
that I want to mention because if
somebody's coming in going okay there's
a ton of libraries like where do I start
with this like what do I use
there is an app called sunflower that
Android created or the Google team
created the Google created Android team
for highlighting jetpack including now
composed by the way where it says all
right here's all these libraries here's
how you can use them here's the benefits
we can give you the link for that we can
post
with the show notes but you can download
it you can start messing around with it
it's updated constantly it seems like
it's a nice fairly simple app
highlighting all these things you can
get I'm quickly Googling it in the
background I can see it's got 16 and a
half thousand stars and yep some commit
to two days ago so it's very active
yeah really really handy to figure out
okay what's out here what can I use
excellent so it doesn't use XML what
sunflower unless they completely
converted it over still does because
it's I mean most apps are still running
XML that has gotten easier with jetpack
as well when you're going ahead and
you're trying to grab components out of
their jetpack offers
both data binding and view binding which
are ways to easily access components
within XML all right I'm gonna use data
binding which is I'm going to send some
object or objects into my view and then
inside the view I can use a certain
syntax to reference values that are in
my objects that are here and that could
be a view model that could just be a
couple of classes whatever it may be or
I can use data binding and say all right
here's my binding I'm going to reference
this component and this component from
my view and assign it values
so instead of having to like do a lookup
based on ID for all your components in
your UI then start assigning values and
everything you can use one of these to
get at it more easily now again if
you're doing compose you're already in
your code you don't have to try to do
some kind of extra library to buying
stuff together you can just say all
right here's my composable sending data
and I've got everything I need right
away but for most apps that are still
using XML
jetpack makes it easier and I think
sunflower should highlight all of that
still I can't imagine they got rid of
all of it at least
thanks and so what's the strap line for
Jetpack compose because I'm thinking of
the word declarative but I can't
remember if that's right or not yep I
it's yeah it's a declarative UI toolkit
the way I always describe it to people
I'm like all right imagine react so the
the JavaScript framework for meta or
Swift UI it's the Android version of
that yeah I remember Amazon as well it's
the same yeah yep same idea and I
remember going through because I've done
react in the past so that's why it was
the first thing I thought of I was going
through a tutorial and they got to one
part where it was like all right we're
handling some of the state here and I'm
like
oh this is react hooks like this is the
exact same code
in kotlin that you would do in
JavaScript for a hook I get this okay
cool I can do that like this is this is
easy enough and so instead of
you know having your here's a full XML
file and here's your UI and again you
can reuse components within XML you have
to remember if it's include or merge or
whatever you may need with compose
you're splitting everything up into
small pieces you've got your little
composables and you're saying all right
here's my composable made of multiple
composables made of more composables all
the way down if you want
and then
you lay everything out that way
yeah and then not similar to flutter
with widgets yep that makes sense
in the JavaScript framework
okay absolutely
and you end up with this unidirectional
data flow with the the different
composables and so you're you're sending
State into and composables for reference
are functions and so you can send in
your parameters to that function again
looking very react like
saying here's here's the state I have
here's all my objects here's everything
there and then sending events back up to
the parent and so it floats to the top
yep yeah that's similar to the rest of
them here
and so you can go ahead and you can have
all these parts here you're sending data
in you're doing events out again the
nice part is like they didn't go ahead
and come up with some crazy new paradigm
like it's things we've seen before it's
a a general approach that works that's
logical for people it makes a lot of
sense so it's it's easier to get into
than it could be otherwise
so would you recommend to start looking
at gem pack compose part of the chat
pack
set of libraries first and then work
backwards when you're thinking about a
traditional Android app versus the
jetpack way I think so I know that's
Google's recommendation
and they're like this is the way we're
going we want to use compose for
everything but to me if you can say all
right my logic's in the code my UI is in
the code everything's within kotlin as
opposed to
oh wait but I'm in here but I'm jumping
out to this layout XML and I'm also
looking at this you know the string XML
over here and the dimension XML over
here like
you know you can still use some of those
if you want but if you can keep your
layouts and UI together it's going to
make things a lot easier and if you're
new to Android and kotlin
it's a lot less that you have to deal
with and again it's just it's nice to
use anyway I almost feel like in a way
it's easier just to come in fresh and
just go with compose
because I know for me like I was using
it a little bit I understand to
declarative UI and I was still going
okay so I developed it like this and
this isn't an XML file I don't do it the
same way as I always have just because
it's Android I need to think about this
a little differently so with coming into
it fresh and just doing the compose part
you're not kind of Breaking Bad Habits
that pop up when you're dealing with
compose now again tons of apps out there
are still using XML if you're looking at
this from a professional perspective you
need to be aware of how the XML works
but
if you have the choice compose is the
way to go both from a just realistic
usability perspective and a Google
recommendation perspective
what would you say to people that have
tried
to create an Android app before jetpack
versus what it's like now just come on
in and have a go yeah absolutely it's a
much different environment um that was I
mean that was part of the reason that I
wanted to I split the book like I did
because I knew okay I love what I can do
with kotlin I've done Android forever
but I'm like I'm gonna go ahead and kind
of focus on Jetpack
because it's all these different ways
that Android dev's gotten easier and for
someone coming to New that maybe doesn't
have that experience of doing Android
Dev with Java and before all these
libraries are here they won't know any
difference but it should be
okay this makes sense it's a little
weird that I'm over in XML but all these
pieces make sense this isn't too bad to
deal with and you know if you've heard
okay it's scary it's way better now if
you haven't heard that it's still a nice
experience to go ahead and be
in the Android ecosystem with even if
you're just looking at XML and Jetpack
way better with that if you're using
compose
it's even smoother in a lot of ways it's
not perfect composers still it's
I believe it's fully released now but
like it's Gonna Change there's things
that are tweaked but it's it's so much
nicer than it was in
2017 2018 versus now
so just to summarize that section it's
the recommended way to develop a
UE now yes go for Jet Pack set of
libraries first
more than likely go for Jetpack compose
straight away it's made the ecosystem
much nicer to work with than what it
used to be even five years ago
it makes things easier because you don't
have this complete separation of
concerns with the look and feel in the
XML that you've got to take back the
data and IDs and tags and things and
struggle that way and as we all know
because we've all we're all developers
nothing's perfect what common mistakes
should we be avoiding with jetpack that
you've come across that you can
recommend I think
there's always going to be some I think
a lot of times it comes down to
understanding your application
understanding your use case
we have an example I'm thinking about
our current APP where our signup flow is
dynamic our backend controls it and part
of my brain's always like well we should
use the navigation component that is
part of Jetpack because with that
instead of having to manually swap out
fragments and do all the stuff you
create a navigation graph and you can
jump between points it's a really nice
tool it works great the fragment isn't
something on your screen so fragment is
and this is something that I've slightly
alluded to earlier but not much of you
have your main activity and then a
fragment is just a view component that
you're using there you can have some
logic and everything but it's a lighter
weight view than you'd have for an
activity and so one of the
recommendations from jetpack is create
an activity and then use the navigation
component to swap between fragments to
get to all the areas you need and so
it's these view pieces that you're using
within your app to
show whatever it is like you know really
it gets a point of your activities like
your main app which has a container and
then your views are all fragments that's
the recommended approach now it's easier
to deal with all of that's there I'm
going back to your navigation sign up
example yep and so with that
we're in a situation where okay we want
to have it where we're showing all these
different fragments we might be jumping
to other parts of the application
different activities that are separate
scopes for what we're dealing with
because in a lot of cases it ends up
being nice to say here is a flow within
my app that can be an activity because
it's its own kind of isolated piece and
then I'll use multiple fragments for the
whole flow with having that Dynamic
ordering that we might have anything
could be in any order really based on
what we get back with the navigation
component you normally would say all
right I have all my
destinations so those may be fragments
or activities
I want to go from this one to this one
which is an action so that navigation
move is an action there and I'm going to
Define that within my nav graph
if you have a consistent flow it works
beautifully you can send parameters you
can get type safe values out of it to
say all right I'm going from A to B and
I want these three parameters in the new
one I just say hey
give you my arguments and I'll use them
in that view it'll be great
we can't do that with that sign up flow
we're like all right we're going to just
avoid using the the navigation component
because it doesn't make sense for a use
case even though
it's kind of like that startup flow that
onboarding flow is exactly what we
should be using in a navigation
component for
our use case doesn't make sense
so I think with all tools make sure you
are trying to solve your problems and
using the tools to do that rather than
here's the tool I should use let's
figure out where I can fit it in
so making sure you understand what your
app needs and where you need to go
thanks for that example I'm presuming
there's some design patterns that are on
the jetpack tutorials and Google
websites well I'm trying to allude to is
is the decision of how to put things
together Made Simple for you or do you
have to decide you know we spoke about
managing State between the different
parts jetpack compose so you have to
figure out do I want that State
Management library from these 10 or you
know are there some best practice design
patterns we can just not spend any
thought and say right let's go for that
but giving you an example of the
navigation component of them maybe some
of them don't fit and you still have to
figure out your use case well I think
that's that's always the case when
you're developing an application you
have to use it or look at how you're
going to use it what makes sense for you
that being said and I remember watching
one of the videos in the team from
Android we're saying we try to leave
things nice and open for people for
foreign
a while to say all right do what you
want with this we'll give you the tools
we'll let you go ahead and
decide what's best and they said you
know what it works better for us to be a
little more opinionated and I think
that's what kind of spurred the
architecture layout that I suggested
before it's what recommends all right
we've got X Y and Z Library you know
you're going ahead you're doing
interactions with the database just use
room and be done with it go in and
that's the it's a effectively an orm
over sqlite that's built into a device
so it's a way to say all right instead
of running queries or whatever I need to
I can say here's a quick SQL statement
it's on a function and I can go ahead
and return something like live data or a
flow from my database which you can
think of as I'm going to create a tunnel
and then when something happens I'm
going to send data down and then react
to it later on in my application
but they're like just start with room
like do that for any local database and
that's what you want to use we're not
going to go and say well we could do it
this way or this way you can do it the
old way
here's the way to approach it if you're
going ahead and you're you're dealing
with fragments you probably want to have
a view model here's how you go ahead and
you can use it you know you want
dependency injection there's other
libraries out there but we're
recommending you use Hilt which is based
on a library called dagger that square
came up with there's all these different
tools and they're like here's what you
need to do here's the library you can
use
go ahead and bring it in if you really
want to do whatever like you have to
look at your own cases but they're going
to say here's probably where you want to
start
do what makes most sense for your
application but this is really probably
your starting point
jet pack
sort of consolidics all that because one
of the time consuming problems with most
Frameworks and ecosystems is right that
looks like the right thing to use let's
go and check out the source control see
how active the project is you know see
how many issues it's got open hopefully
jetpack makes that all so much easier
you can just say right if that does what
it says on the 10 I can presume it's
going to be stable I presume it's going
to be around for at least the next three
to five years that I need to support our
commercial apps or apps yep and it's
it's all out there and the thing that's
nice about the jetpack libraries is
they're versioned independently I think
I had mentioned this earlier but if you
say all right I want to go ahead and I
want to add in let's say I want to add
room and I'm adding work manager for
background scheduling and I want the
navigation components and some of the
kotlin extensions for fragments and view
models and all these pieces
I can bring those all in to my
application
they can be on their own version so
let's say all right I get everything in
here and then a new version of room
comes out but I'm not ready to grab it
yet
I can leave it alone oh I want an update
for work manager I'll just update work
manager and I'll call it good they're
all these separate pieces that are out
there and so they are very clear of okay
this is a stable release this is a Beta
release Alpha release whatever it might
be
but they're all out there they're all
version independently and they're all
available for what you need what's
shifted even from when I did the book of
here's the pieces we're focusing on with
jetpack the old libraries are still out
there they still work they still do what
they need to there just hasn't been a
need to expand on them is there a
problem with versioning things before
jetpack well what would happen is a lot
of times you would have the support
libraries for Android and those were
more tied to a particular version of the
OS and like okay here's where we're
backboarding things but it was like
here's the whole support Library what if
I just want the newer part of this
section but not this one now it's split
up into smaller pieces so you can get
exactly what you want but you don't
bring in like you don't bring in jet
pack you bring in all the pieces that
make sense for your app because if
you're bringing all of Jetpack all of a
sudden your app's way bigger because you
have all these extra libraries and
things that you don't need
and so you can have those pieces
separately you can version them
separately so you upgrade when you're
available and it puts you in as the
developer more in control of what's
going into your app and what you're
using yeah and size is a concern for
shipping across the network and things
from play absolutely that'll get you
into trouble
okay I'm going to start wrapping up the
show so it sounds like jetpack is a safe
bet to choose for your next Androids
application do you agree absolutely
jetpack it's going to keep evolving it's
going to keep changing but the
architecture they recommend the tools I
recommend make a lot of sense for even a
new application right now
and Jetpack composers that something is
another safe bet absolutely the team is
saying this is where we're going this is
what we're gonna have this is the way we
want you to write UI going forward we're
done with the old XML style you can
still use it but the new effort that
we're putting in is focused on compose
and so this is where you're going to
want to go for a native development for
quite a while
excellent thank you Michael so I've got
one last question I'm going to sneak in
before I properly wrap up this is from
co-host
when an organization is also making an
IOS app which pretty much everyone has
to do is there anything they do
differently to be able to share code or
logic which may also affect how they
build their back end so potentially
maybe your back ends an API you know and
you're calling into it from
Android or jetpack or iOS
have you got any experience with that
that's part of what we're doing right
now with the current APP we've got an
Android app we've got an IOS app we have
a back end we have a smaller web app
and one of the things we try to do is
any logic because we have future parity
between both platforms a lot of places
are going to be just like that
as much as we can we try to put our
logic in the back end in our apis and so
a little bit how you're developing your
Android app where it's like here's my
view
and here's my view model and I just know
all right I ask for data it gives me a
back I'm not worried about where it's
coming from how it's being dealt with
what the rules are anything like that I
just say here's my state here's what I
need send that to me we do something
similar where we say hey back end here's
what I need here's where I am right now
or in a lot of cases you already know
where I am here's who I am you tell me
what I need and then they send us the
logic and so instead of Android and iOS
each having to try to deal with all
these complex business rules based on
what we know about a user we let the
back end take care of that
now if you want to go more direct and
say all right we really just want to
share logic that's coming on we want to
share data coming from the back end
whatever it might be maybe you start
looking at kotlin multi-platform which
is a little different than your your
cross-platform libraries in that you can
use kotlin multi-platform to more or
less build a separate library that works
on Android and iOS
and you can fit it into both
applications and so now you've got one
spot where maybe how you hit the back
end is there or how you grab language
values from the back end is in there and
that can be shared as well
what sort of things do you ask of your
own back ends if you're allowed to say
in particular when we're dealing with
language
we allow the the back end to determine
how things are written for us which has
a couple benefits one
it makes it easier for Android and iOS
to just say oh you've got X Y and Z copy
you go ahead and send it to me and we'll
display the language that you gave us we
don't have to worry about anything other
than here's a key for the language
coming in and I'm going to display it
also if we're in a situation where again
talking from a financial perspective we
have to be very careful about how we say
things from a legal side
if something needs to be changed like
immediately
it's hard to go ahead and get a new app
version out it's not hard like it takes
a day or so but you can't do something
quickly if that's on the back end
we can update it faster plus if we say
all right we're going to update this
language and we're gonna have it for
all these versions of the app you change
that in the back end we don't have to
make app updates and people that already
have the app will now see the new
language they'll see the new logic the
apps are a lot more static than a
backend can be because you're not in
control of it it's on someone's device
you can kind of force them to upgrade
but like it's not a guarantee that you
can go ahead and
say hey you need to have this version of
the app because we want this thing
they're like well I'm just not going to
update right now because I don't feel
like it unless you want to lock them out
of the app
you don't have a lot of control if you
can instead have the back end control
all right here's a new feature here's
new language here's again how that
signup flow works I can go ahead and I
can turn pieces on and off of the signup
flow without touching the app
it makes a lot easier to test things out
make updates and really get the
experience that I want for users very
quickly without needing them to do
anything
yeah so as part of your architecture
design your business logic or business
use case type thing exactly so I think
we've done a great job of covering
why you should develop software natively
for Android just to summarize that again
was you know your teams your expertise
devices you're going on to
Etc
and why you should use Android jetpack
in the first place but if there was one
thing you'd like a software engineer to
remember from our show what would you
like that to be Michael
I think it's just
Android development now is a really
really nice experience like it's not
perfect there's quirks there's weirdness
but
it's gotten really really good kotlin is
great to work with
and some of the headaches that people
may have talked about in the past or may
have you know the horror stories that
were being told a lot of those are gone
and the end of the day you get to sit
here and have a mobile device and create
really really nice powerful apps
for that device for people to use
and you can do it in a way where you're
not always pulling your hair out because
of let's say limitations within the
framework so I'd say Android development
now it's in a really good spot it's
really enjoyable kotlin enables a ton of
that jetpacks made things better
composers made things even better from
that and so it's a really nice ecosystem
now
thanks I think that was more than one
thing but that's good sorry was there
anything we missed that you think we
should mention again probably one of
those I could go on for another 45
minutes but I think we definitely
covered it yeah so you're getting an
Android use Catlin use the jetpack
libraries use compose and you're going
to be in a good spot going forward for
quite a while yeah I'll make sure we get
the sunflower app link in the show notes
and some of the other stuff we spoke
about I'll talk about the after so where
can people find out more we can follow
you on Twitter but you know how should
they get in touch if they want to join
you about anything so I'm on Twitter as
Fazio Dev
and otherwise the book is available at
pragprog.com
so you can go on there should be able to
get a coupon code onto the the show
notes as well I'm going to work with the
team to make sure that's available and
then otherwise just the
developer.android.com has a ton of
resources there
go there check out the documentation
check out sunflower go through the code
Labs there are code labs for compose and
a bunch of the different jetpack
libraries there's ones on co-routines
all these different little hour-long
mini classes that you can download and
walk through and get your your kotlin
skills your Android skills improve just
from walking through those I think those
are all great tools that are out there
for people that want to learn more about
Android yeah it's really rich I've
looked at sometimes myself but
personally I would buy the book
definitely buy the book I'm biased but
yeah I think it's great Michael thank
you for coming on the show as always
it's been a real pleasure this is Gavin
Henry for software engineering radio and
thank you for listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening
[Music]
foreign